Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. All right, today's דף daf is
נ"א nun aleph and
we pick up right after the משנה mishna here, and the משנה
mishna is going through all of these issues in terms of מאמר
maimar after מאמר, maimar, גט get after גט, get, יבום yibum after
יבום, yibum, or ביאה biah after ביאה biah according to the language
of the משנה, mishna, חליצה chalitza after חליצה. chalitza. The basic principle
to know, and of course we're going to work through the details,
is that מאמר maimar and גט get are rabbinic. Obviously they parallel
the classic forms of marriage and divorce. מאמר maimar is actually an
act of קידושין, kidushin, הרי את מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet li.
גט get is a גט, get, but of course here we're dealing
in the context of יבום. yibum. So in this context, they operate
rabbinically. And יבום yibum and חליצה chalitza are דאורייתא. d'oraissa.
And therefore the question is, is that after יבום yibum and חליצה
chalitza presumably the act is already done, although the גמרא Gemara deals
with cases, the משנה mishna deals with cases about ביאה פסולה biah
psula and חליצה פסולה chalitza psula and so on. But basically, after
ביאה biah and חליצה, chalitza, we're talking about that the real act
is already done. So there there's a pretty much of a consensus
that an act done after ביאה biah and חליצה chalitza is not
meaningful. The question is, what about an act done after the rabbinic
גט get or the rabbinic מאמר? maimar? Does that still have meaning
in terms of implications about what it does to affect the status
of the various people that are involved? So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
says, just to review where we're up to without going through the
details but just to frame it, אין גט אחר גט ולא מאמר
אחר מאמר. ein get achar get v'lo maimar achar maimar. That once
those acts are done, nothing afterward has consequence, even though those are
only operating on a rabbinic level. And then obviously, ולא ביאה אחר
ביאה ולא חליצה אחר חליצה.
v'lo biah achar biah v'lo chalitza
achar chalitza. The חכמים Chachamim disagree with the גט get and the
מאמר. maimar. יש גט אחר גט ויש מאמר אחר מאמר, yesh get
achar get v'yesh maimar achar maimar, because those are rabbinic, so they
do not completely serve end the process of what's going on as
opposed to ביאה biah after ביאה biah and יבום yibum and חליצה
chalitza after חליצה, chalitza, those the second stage is not yet meaningful.
Okay, so one is sort of how absolute is that first
act with something that comes afterwards. But then the other question is
also about what's the thing coming afterwards? Because we talk about four
things, right? גט, get, מאמר, maimar, חליצה, chalitza, and יבום. yibum. After
act one, can always come any series of the other types of
acts, either to the same woman or to a different woman or
from the same brother-in-law or from a different brother-in-law. We get to
play with all of those possibilities, which is what the משנה mishna
sort of works out. Okay, we won't review the whole משנה, mishna,
that was all of yesterday's דף, daf, but just that's basically the
framework and then we're going to go through it. But again to
remember that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says basically after the first act,
even that, the later acts are not meaningful as a general rule,
and the חכמים Chachamim say that's true by ביאה biah and חליצה,
chalitza, not by מאמר maimar and גט. get. So let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara bottom of נ"א עמוד ב'. nun aleph
amud bet. Already there's a question? I didn't even say anything yet.
Yes.
I just wanted to clarify from yesterday. Are we talking about... are
they two different types of גטין? gittin? That is to say, a
גט get after קידושין kidushin is דאורייתא d'oraissa and this is a
rabbinic גט? get? Or גט get always considered to be דרבנן? derabanan?
No, גט, get, a גט get in the context of when a
woman is awaiting יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza is דרבנן. derabanan. What
do you mean? A גט get is דאורייתא d'oraissa in all of
מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin in normal marriage. That's what I said. In
this context, מאמר maimar and גט get are the classic קידושין kidushin
and גטין gittin that operate at a דאורייתא d'oraissa plane. But in
the context of יבום yibum and חליצה, chalitza, they're operating דרבנן. derabanan.
It's not a rabbinic גט. get.
Yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. No, it's what do you mean? It's a rabbinic גט. get.
It's a גט get that is done, executed as if it were
דאורייתא d'oraissa in the same way as קידושין kidushin and follows the
same procedures. הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet li, everything is
done properly. But because it's taking place in the context of a
יבום yibum situation, it's not meaningful דאורייתא. d'oraissa. But it's not that
it's done differently, it's just that its meaning is not דאורייתא. d'oraissa.
It doesn't mean... yeah, yeah, exactly.
The meaning, my question was about its meaning or its import, not
about its formal execution.
Correct. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, last of the
narrow lines on נ"א עמוד ב'. nun aleph amud bet. עד כאן
לא פליגי אלא בגט אחר גט ומאמר אחר
מאמר.
Ad kan lo peligi ela b'get achar get u'maimar
achar maimar. Okay, so the debate is גט get following a גט,
get, a מאמר maimar following a מאמר. maimar. That's the debate of
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and the חכמים Chachamim where רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel says it's nothing, the חכמים Chachamim say it's meaningful.
אבל גט אחד ביבמה ומאמר אחד ביבמה מהני. aval get echad b'yevama
u'maimar echad b'yevama mahani. Now first we want to just establish the
ground rules, which is where is this idea that there's such something
meaningful called a גט get or something meaningful called מאמר maimar by
a sister-in-law? Now we know it's rabbinic, although I'll remind you that
בית שמאי Beit Shammai holds that there's even a דאורייתא d'oraissa idea
of מאמר, maimar, ולקחה לו לאשה ויבמה v'lakacha lo l'isha v'yibmah
according to the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, ולקחה לו לאשה v'lakacha lo l'isha means
that even there's an idea of actual ליקוחין, likuchin, of actual קידושין
kidushin that apply by יבום. yibum. But anyway, that's בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai, we'll see that hopefully at the end of today's דף, daf,
but basically it's assumed that this is all rabbinic. So let's first
establish where is this rabbinic concept of גט get and מאמר maimar
by a sister-in-law.
מהני מאי טעמא? Mahani mai ta'ama? Why did the rabbis say that...
It could be some meaning of a גט get *get* by a
sister-in-law. Now what does it mean מהני *mehani*? מהני *Mehani* meaning without
doing two things. Don't do a גט get *get* and then a
גט get *get*, or מאמר ma'amar. *ma'amar* and a מאמר ma'amar *ma'amar*,
or מאמר ma'amar *ma'amar* and a גט get *get*. Just a גט
get *get*! Where do you know? Where did the Rabbis come up
with this idea to create a גט get *get* by a sister-in-law?
Where'd they come up with this idea to create מאמר maamar, *ma'amar*
by a sister-in-law? What's the nature of this institution? Okay, now the
basic meaning of the word מהני *mehani*, מהני *mehani* obviously doesn't mean
the full מהני *mehani*. It doesn't mean that a גט get *get*
does the effect of a חליצה chalitzah *chalitza* that you need דאורייתא
de-oraisa *de'oraita* חליצה chalitzah, *chalitza*. It doesn't mean מאמר maamar. *ma'amar* does
the effect of יבום yibum *yibum* that you need the act of
sex. But what it means is that it has implications. So for
example, the implications of giving a גט get *get* to a sister-in-law
is that now it closes off the opportunities of doing יבום yibum,
*yibum*. פסלה כל האחים *pasla kol ha'achim*, right? You can't do יבום
yibum *yibum*, the other brothers can't do יבום yibum. *yibum*. One can't
marry the relatives, exactly, it's as if it's
the man's divorced wife. מאמר maamar *ma'amar* has the effect of,
well A, for relatives, that now this woman is like a quasi-wife,
the זיקה zika, *zika* wasn't enough in terms of issues of relatives,
and also has the effect of, for example, preventing doing יבום yibum
*yibum* with another one of the co-wives because you've already created this
relationship with this co-wife and so on. So all these things have
halakhic import. מהני *Mehani* is not to the end but they have
halakhic meaning. Okay, so מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama* אמר רבנן rabanan, *amar
rabanan* גט get *get* ביבמה *b'yevama* מהני *mehani*? Why did the Rabbis
allow for this institution of גט get *get* by a sister-in-law? משום
דמהני בעלמא *mishum d'mehani b'alma*, because normally a גט get, *get* works,
right? If it's a full wife and a גט get *get* works,
we're going to give it some meaning in the context of this
case of זיקה zika, *zika* and the sister-in-law. דאי אמרת לא מהני
*de'ee amrat la mehani*, because were you to say, "Nah, in the
context of sister-in-law, we don't recognize גט get. *get*. גט get *get*
is meaningless." That would be a natural thing to say, but
אמרי amri, *amri*, people will say, "גט get, להוציא וחליצה להוציא *get
l'hotzi v'chalitza l'hotzi*." So they'll say, "Look, a גט get *get* normally
divorces a wife, even a full wife, and a חליצה chalitzah, *chalitza*
divorces a sister-in-law." So ומדגט לא מהני *umide'get la mehani*, they'll see
a guy give a גט get *get* to a sister-in-law and they'll
see that it's meaningless. They'll see that afterwards he can even do
יבום yibum. *yibum*. So they'll also say, "חליצה chalitzah נמי לא מהני
*chalitza nami la mehani*." So they'll say, "Well, חליצה chalitzah *chalitza* is
meaningless. The only thing you can do is יבום yibum *yibum*. גט
get *get* doesn't work, חליצה chalitzah *chalitza* doesn't work."
It worked with חליצה chalitzah *chalitza* in a normal marriage though.
All right,
ואתי למיבעל אחר חליצה chalitza *v'atei l'miba'al achar chalitza*, and then we'll
do a
חליצה chalitza. *chalitza* and they'll say, "Yeah, but we saw another guy
give a גט get *get* and then he did יבום yibum *yibum*,
so this guy could do חליצה chalitza *chalitza* and then do יבום
yibum *yibum*." Of course it's like funny, I mean it's מפורש *mefurash*
in the פסוקים *pesukim* or whatever, but okay, it just gets confused
if we have if we do it like that. Again, I don't
know, to me it's more confusing if you keep mixing categories.
It's essentially, I mean it seems like the whole idea of recognizing
a גט get *get* is because of mistake as practice. Yeah, I
don't think the Rabbis made this up, "Oh, maybe you should give
a גט get *get*," right? It seems like that it came to
be because people
started doing it.
They would be in a situation of חליצה chalitza *chalitza* and give
a גט get *get*. And so then the Rabbis post-facto had to
recognize that because of this.
Right, it's an interesting question like where did this start. Did the
Rabbis want to start this process? Right, did the Rabbis want to
start this process? Because also this is a process that documents it.
You know, look, the whole institution as we've said of יבום yibum
*yibum*, you know, is like is challenging, right? Because of like, I
mean, the whole idea that you go straight to like the sex
and to the consummation and the marriage and you don't precede it
with like this type of a קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* which is what
מאמר maamar *ma'amar* does. And there's actually some sense that מאמר maamar.
*ma'amar* is something the Rabbis actually wanted, you know. So I think
it's an interesting question. You're right. The way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
here is framing it is like people are doing it and we
have to we can't outright reject it, you know. I'm not sure
that all the other sort of sources indicate that it was a
grassroots type of a thing that we couldn't like completely reject, you
know. There might have other things make it sound like the Rabbis
actually wanted there to be these additional type of instruments for sort
of starting the process or whatever. But you're right. The way the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here frames it, it sounds like people are doing
it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, "ומאי טעמא אמר רבנן
rabanan מאמר maamar ביבמה מהני *u'mai ta'ama amar rabanan ma'amar b'yevama mehani*?"
Why did they say מאמר maamar, *ma'amar* works like, you know, enough
to make her quasi-marriage? "משום דמהני בעלמא *mishum d'mehani b'alma*," because normally
we're talking about an act of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*. "דאי אמרת לא
מהני *de'ee amrat la mehani*," if they'll say, "No, this is meaningless
in the case of sister-in-law," so אמרי *amri*, "מאמר maamar לקנות וביאה
לקנות *ma'amar l'knot u'be'ah l'knot*." They'll say, "Let's take a look. קידושין
*kiddushin* normally works and ביאה bi'ah *be'ah* normally works. So ומדמאמר לא
מהני *umide'ma'amar la mehani*, and if the קידושין *kiddushin* doesn't work by
a sister-in-law, ביאה bi'ah נמי לא מהני *be'ah nami la mehani*." So
therefore the act of sex won't work. I mean, again, I don't
know how they read the פסוקים *pesukim* and what they think would
work, but anyway, it'll obviously raise a lot of questions because they'll
assume if the stronger stuff doesn't work, like the classic stuff doesn't
work, the weaker stuff won't work also, and it'll just lead to
a lot of confusion. ואתי למיבעל אחר ביאה bi'ah *v'atei l'miba'al achar
be'ah*, and they'll say, "Okay, one guy did an act of sex
with his sister-in-law, but yeah, that doesn't work, קידושין *kiddushin* doesn't work,
so then go ahead and have sex with the other sister-in-law, you
know, do יבום yibum? *yibum* with her." They won't realize it was
already binding with the first one. Okay, so basically we need to
let these things work somewhat because people are anyway going to assume
that they're effective and therefore it'll be too confusing if they don't
have any any effect. Essentially, since normally they work even at a
stronger level, even without a preceding זיקה zika *zika*. Okay, ו *u*...
ומאי טעמא אמרי רבנן, rabanan so that's point number one, that we
have these institutions of גט get and מאמר. maamar, ומאי טעמא אמרי
רבנן ביאה פסולה יש אחריה כלום? U'mai ta'ama amrei rabanan bi'ah pesulah
yesh achareiha klum? So why do the Rabbis say that if the
ביאה bi'ah was somehow problematic, meaning that it came after something had
been done to the זיקה, let's say there was a גט get
given to one of the sister-in-laws and then ביאה bi'ah to the
next, that then the act that follows it is somehow significant? That's
the end of the משנה. mishna. To remind you, if we look
quickly at the end of the משנה mishna that we just read,
it says like
this: אין
אחר חליצה כלום בין בתחילה בין באמצע בין בסוף.
Ein achar chalitzah
klum, bein betechilah, bein be'emtza, bein besof. והבעילה, Veha-bi'ilah, but the after-effect,
the end of the משנה mishna says, going back about five lines
before the lines get wide: בזמן שהיא בתחילה אין אחריה כלום. Bizman
she-hi betechilah, ein achareiha klum. If you start with an act of
sex with the brother-in-law and sister-in-law, then that's it, and the act
of יבום yibbum. was done, end of story. Nothing afterwards counts. But
באמצע ובסוף, be'emtza u-besof, however, if it didn't come right at the
beginning, if however something happened, like for example,
you gave a גט get to one wife and to one of
the sister-in-laws and then ביאה bi'ah with the other, that's באמצע, be'emtza,
and then you did something after that, and then after that ביאה
bi'ah you did, I don't know, a מאמר maamar with a third
wife or some other thing, or that's באמצע, be'emtza, or בסוף, besof,
or just those two, יש אחריה כלום, yesh achareiha klum, that afterwards
some act will still be meaningful. So without getting back to yesterday's
דף, daf, believe me, we're going to do enough unpacking of that
in a minute. What you see though is, is that when a
ביאה bi'ah comes at the beginning of the process and is the
act of יבום, yibbum? then we're done. But if however something preceded
it that affected some of the relationships and the זיקה, even at
a דרבנן derabanan level, like a גט get was given to one
woman and then a ביאה bi'ah to the next, it's not like
the ביאה bi'ah ends the story. And things that happen afterwards still
have some import, even though דאורייתא de-oraisa they don't, even though דאורייתא
de-oraisa once the יבום yibbum, is done, we're done, but דרבנן, derabanan,
once that ביאה bi'ah, followed some other type of a thing, it's
not seen of as a full ביאה bi'ah or a ביאה bi'ah
that was acting on a normal type of a זיקה and therefore
things that follow still have import. So the גמרא Gemara says why
is that? Again, the details were yesterday and hopefully we'll revisit them
today, but at least that's the broad strokes. So the גמרא says
like this: ומאי טעמא אמרו רבנן ביאה פסולה יש אחריה כלום?
U'mai ta'ama amru rabanan
bi'ah pesulah yesh achareiha klum? After a quote-unquote invalid ביאה, bi'ah a
ביאה bi'ah that was not coming like straight on the heels of,
you know, either following a מאמר maamar or immediately afterwards, but came
after let's say a גט get was given to another woman, to
another one of the co-wives. So how do we know that therefore
it's not finished and there can be acts done afterwards that are
meaningful? So אמרי, אי ביאה אחר גט היא, ei bi'ah achar get
hi, because let's look at the scenarios of what would be a
ביאה פסולה. bi'ah pesulah. One would be you gave a גט get,
to one wife and one sister and then did ביאה bi'ah with
the other sister. So then גזירה ביאה אחר גט משום ביאה אחר
חליצה. gezeirah bi'ah achar get mishum bi'ah achar chalitzah. Because the Rabbis
have to say that that ביאה bi'ah we're going to have to
recognize as somewhat problematic,
because if instead of the גט get you did a חליצה chalitza.
with co-wife number one, with sister-in-law number one, then the ביאה bi'ah
afterwards would be completely invalid, right? The person had already done חליצה,
chalitza we're done. Okay, then there's no longer an act of יבום.
yibbum, So now if he gives a גט get to sister-in-law one
and does ביאה biah with sister-in-law two, at a דאורייתא de-oraisa level
he's done יבום yibbum, with sister-in-law number two, right? דאורייתא de-oraisa that's
the יבום. yibbum... But we can't sort of allow that to work,
we're going to have to force him to give a גט get
and the whole thing, we have to problematize that. And why do
we problematize that? Because although it's true דאורייתא de-oraisa he's done יבום
yibbum. with sister-in-law two, if instead of the גט get to sister-in-law
one he had done חליצה, chalitza, then this
would not, he would not have been in an act of יבום
yibbum. with wife number two.
Okay, so we have to therefore problematize it. Is this clear? Okay.
Right? You got ראובן, Reuven, he dies. Okay, who are his wives?
I don't know, שרה Sarah and רבקה. Rifkah.
Okay, unrelated. Okay, and you have שמעון. Shimon. So if שמעון Shimon
here, right, if שמעון Shimon does חליצה chalitza here, then he's done.
And then any act of יבום yibbum, here of ביאה biah would
be meaningless, right?
And that would be actually an
איסור issur of אשת אח eshes ach or an איסור issur of
כיון שלא בנה שוב לא יבנה. keivan shelo banah shuv lo yivneh.
Okay, so if instead he
did גט, get
okay,
if he did גט get and that was
stage number one, and then he did ביאה biah.
and that was stage number two, דאורייתא de'oraita this is יבום yibbum
and he should continue living with רבקה Rifkah and that was meaningless
and go on with it, right?
But דרבנן derabanan would say
no, we're going to call
this ביאה פסולה bi'ah pesulah and he's actually not going to be
able to remain here with רבקה Rifkah and he's going to have
to give her a גט. get Okay, why are we going to
demand that? Why don't we just say he did a good act
of יבום? Because this case, again, the problem is that גט get,
and חליצה chalitza are easily confused. And if we allow him to
stay in this relationship, it'll be confused with a case where he's
done חליצה chalitza here and then obviously that will not be, that
will be an unacceptable relationship, right? So therefore we have to make
this ביאה פסולה bi'ah pesulah if it followed גט, get because if
it followed חליצה chalitza clearly it. would not be meaningful. And once
we make it be a פסול pasul *psul*, we're going to say
that therefore it's not, there's things can come afterwards that are still
meaningful. We don't realize the relationship as fully having been consummated yet.
I don't understand, say, full force of the דרבנן derabanan. *derabbanan* of
לא *lo*? No. No. But if it like no, דאורייתא de'oraita *de'oraisa*
he really is. That's why he would have to give her גט
get *get*. He's not uprooting anything, but he'd have to give a
גט get *get*. They just don't let him stay in the relationship.
Yes. So they are they are deliberately because of the concern they
are deliberately nullifying the intent of ביאה biah *biah* of... Again, they're
not nullifying. They're They They He needs a גט get *get* if
he has... Oh, they're going against the purpose of it. Yeah, yeah.
That's true, that's only true. So he's got he's got to go
back and do חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*. Yeah, well he has to do
חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*. Well, he could do חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* with the
first one. Well, biblically he doesn't, right? Because biblically he's done יבום
*yibum* and he's done. דרבנן derabanan *derabbanan* he does, right? Okay. So,
to So, just חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* with one. Okay. So with the
first one, let's say, he gives a גט get *get* to רבקה
*Rivka* and goes back and does חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*... I'm getting I'll
have to double-check that.
All right. I get a little lost on all these. You mean
he goes back and...
It was yesterday.
Yeah, he gave her a גט get, *get*. Oh no, because כיון
שלא בנה שוב לא יבנה *keivan shelo banah shuv lo yivneh*. Once
he hasn't done יבום *yibum*... No, he can't. Okay, he can't. Yeah.
Okay. So the משנה mishna *mishnah* says like this. So, וביא אחר
חליצה chalitza, או שביא אחר חליצה chalitza וביא אחר מאמר maamar היא
*u'bei-ach achar chalitzah o she'bei-ach achar chalitzah u'bei-ach achar ma'amar hi*. Let's
say he had done מאמר maamar *ma'amar*, right? Here to to שרה
*Sarah*. Now again, that's meaningless דאורייתא de'oraita. *de'oraisa* and he should be
able to go ahead and stay in the relationship with רבקה *Rivka*.
Except מאמר maamar *ma'amar* is a pseudo-type of a יבום *yibum*. And
had he done יבום *yibum*, he wouldn't be able to be in
a relationship with רבקה *Rivka* because בית אחד הוא בונה ואינו בונה
שני בתים *bayis echad hu boneh ve-eino boneh shenei batim*. So since
if it followed מאמר maamar *ma'amar* we have to treat it as
an invalid ביאה biah *biah* because we have to treat it as
if it had followed יבום *yibum*. Okay. אי ביא אחר מאמר maamar
היא גזירת ביא אחר מאמר maamar, משום ביא אחר ביאה biah *ee
bei-ach achar ma'amar hi gezera bei-ach achar ma'amar mishum bei-ach achar biah*.
ומאי טעמא אמרו רבנן האי חליצה פסולה chalitza pesula, אינה אחריה כלום
*u'mai ta'ama amru rabbanan hai chalitzah psulah ein achareha klum*? Why do
Rabbis say that if it's a חליצה chalitza פסולה *chalitzah psulah*, if
חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* followed some other thing, then nothing like it completely
removes any זיקה *zikah*? But the ביאה biah *biah* afterwards does not
completely remove any ביאה biah *biah*... any any זיקה *zikah* and you
still have some some type of a quasi or problematic stage. אמרי
מאי נגזור *amri mai nigzar*? Because what do you want to be
נגזור *nigzar*? We've already explained why the ביאה biah *biah* that follows
something is not a hundred percent. But why should we what should
we say in a case of חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*? מאי נגזור *mai
nigzar*? נגזור חליצה chalitza אחר גט get משום חליצה chalitza אחר חליצה
chalitza *nigzar chalitzah achar get mishum chalitzah achar chalitzah*. So let's say,
okay, so what would be the case? The case would be that
first he did here, a, number one is he did a גט
get *get* and then number two is he did חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*.
And we'll call it חליצה chalitza פסולה *chalitzah psulah* and maybe not
recognize it as a you know and see see it that something
can still come afterwards. Okay. But what would what would be the
case? Let's say it would be the חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* to גט
get *get* and one says well this is problematic. Why is it
problematic? Because a גט get *get* case will be confused with a
חליצה *chalitzah* case. But if it's a חליצה *chalitzah* after חליצה *chalitzah*,
nothing can go wrong. What's going to go wrong in a חליצה
*chalitzah* after חליצה *chalitzah*? He was already been done with stage number
one and doing another חליצה *chalitzah* is not Doing a ביאה biah
*biah* after you've done something else, either done יבום *yibum* or חליצה
*chalitzah* with wife one, then trying to do יבום *yibum* with wife
number two or sister number two is problematic because you've already finished
with whatever you've done with number one. But doing a חליצה *chalitzah*
second doesn't get you into trouble. חליצה *chalitzah*'s not a forbidden act
like sex is with a sister-in-law. So it says, so אמרי מאי
נגזור *amri mai nigzar*. What should we make? מאי נגזור *mai nigzar*?
נגזור חליצה אחר גט get משום חליצה אחר חליצה *nigzar chalitzah achar
get mishum chalitzah achar chalitzah*. Because don't say חליצה *chalitzah* after גט
get *get* is problematic because what if it came after חליצה *chalitzah*?
כל כי הני תחלוץ ותצא *kol ki hani tachlotz ve-teizei*. So okay,
make her do a חליצה *chalitzah* with a hundred sister-in-laws. What do
we care? It's not going to be problematic. נגזור *nigzar*, of course
you could say it's problematic because it makes the woman consider the
חלוצה *chalutzah* and makes her אסורה *asurah* to a כהן kohen *kohen*.
Okay. נגזור חליצה אחר מאמר משום חליצה אחר ביאה chalitza achar maamar
mishum chalitza achar biah. *nigzar chalitzah achar ma'amar mishum chalitzah achar biah*.
Okay, well what let's say he did here מאמר maamar *ma'amar*. Okay,
then and then he did חליצה *chalitzah*. Well, and that might get
confused with a case of a יבום *yibum* case. But it's the
same story. Good, he did יבום *yibum*, he's in a relationship with
שרה *Sarah*. He did מאמר maamar *ma'amar*, he's in a relationship with
שרה *Sarah*. Do חליצה *chalitzah* with רבקה *Rivka*, doesn't hurt anybody. Doing
the חליצה *chalitzah* at the end, חליצה *chalitzah*'s not a problematic act,
right? ביאה biah *biah*, sex with a woman you're not allowed to
be married to or have sex with or whatever is problematic. Doing
חליצה *chalitzah* that follows something like מאמר maamar *ma'amar* or or גט
get *get* or יבום *yibum* or חליצה *chalitzah*... All right, it's a
silly act, but it doesn't hurt anybody, so therefore it's not we're
not going to problematize it. So חליצה אחר מאמר chalitza achar maamar.
משום חליצה אחר ביאה biah *chalitzah achar ma'amar mishum chalitzah achar biah*.
אטו חליצה אחר מאמר maamar מי לא בעי גט get למאמרו *atu
chalitzah achar ma'amar mi lo ba'ei get le-ma'amaro*? So חליצה אחר ביאה
נמי בעי גט לביאתו chalitza achar biah nami ba'ei get leviahto. *chalitzah
achar biah nami ba'ei get le-be'iaso*. So let's say when we said
he did a חליצה *chalitzah* after מאמר maamar *ma'amar*. Now by the
way, remember that although we're saying like doing an extra חליצה *chalitzah*
is silly, but the actual case that... You've done here, חליצה after
גט get. or חליצה after מאמר, maamar the thing that actually is
binding דאורייתא de'oraita is the חליצה. Okay, so he did a חליצה
after מאמר. maamar So we're going to say the חליצה is totally
fine, nothing comes afterwards, you're done with the חליצה. חליצה finishes, it's
like it's not חליצה פסולה, anything afterwards is okay. But we'll say,
but one minute, but if he had done a, but if he's
going to think that he can just walk away because you've done
a חליצה, you walk away. Well, let's say it had been a
חליצה after יבום. He wouldn't be able to just walk away because
he'd still be in a relationship with Sarah. He'd still have to
give Sarah a גט get, if he wanted a to walk away.
So the גמרא is saying, but okay, but in the case of
מאמר maamar as well, because he did a מאמר maamar, we say
he still needs to give a גט get? to Sarah. So there's
no reason to be גוזר gozer חליצה after מאמר. maamar, Oh, we
shouldn't allow him to say you're done here because it might be
somewhat problematic. What if it was a case of יבום? Well, in
the case of יבום, in both cases, whether it's מאמר maamar after,
חליצה after מאמר, maamar חליצה after יבום, he's always going to have
to give a גט get to Sarah. So there's no reason though
to continue to problematize חליצה once we're demanding that he sever the
relationship with Sarah. He doesn't need the חליצה in this case of
יבום, right? Once he does a יבום... Yeah, but but we're afraid
that חליצה after מאמר maamar will lead to a case of חליצה
after יבום. So כעת, ka'et, let's read it. חליצה אחר מאמר maamar
משום חליצה אחר ביאה. biah, אתו atu חליצה אחר מאמר. maamar By
the חליצה after מאמר, maamar it's true, we're not problematizing the חליצה,
but we're not saying you're done, we're not saying you walk away,
we're saying מי לא בעי גט למאמרה? mi lo ba'ei get lemaamarah?
You still have to go back and give a גט get to
Sarah. So therefore that's what we're normally going to demand. But we
say אין אחר חליצה כלום, ein achar chalitza klum, after the חליצה
you're done. So חליצה אחר ביאה נמי בעי גט get לביאתו. So
we have, there's no reason to make a גזירה gezeira because the
same will be true after חליצה after יבום. You have to go
ahead and give a גט get, if he wanted if he wanted
to free himself from Sarah. So basically what it's saying is, again,
this idea is ביאה פסולה, biah pesula, a ביאה that follows some
previous thing, right, is still not considered to be like you're not
done. There's still some remnant there and therefore it can allow for
other acts afterwards to be meaningful because a ביאה that follows some
something else, חליצה or יבום, is a problematic ביאה. So the ביאה
after a מאמר maamar or גט get remains problematic, you're not done.
Whereas a חליצה that follows מאמר maamar or גט get is not
problematic. You are totally done because חליצה doesn't hurt anybody. It doesn't
like it doesn't problematize the situation. It doesn't mean that it doesn't
mean that you don't have to address what you did before. You
might have to address what you did before and go ahead and
give a גט get to Sarah, but the חליצה afterwards, you're basic,
you know, you're basically done. Alright? People get this more or less?
Okay, fine. Alright, so we basically got the idea that why they
instituted or allowed for the institutions of מאמר maamar and גט and
why a the חליצה that follows some type of an act is
fundamentally unproblematic because חליצה is itself doesn't hurt anybody. I mean it
hurts the woman in terms of her status as a כהן which
we're ignoring, but basically it's not what will not lead to like
a serious act of עריות arayot and therefore we can allow it
to be end the process. You might have to pick up some
of the pieces from before but it basically ends the process, where
a ביאה that could be an act of עריות arayot based on
what happened before doesn't end the process and is still seen as
as you know problematic and still not complete and therefore things afterwards
can be meaningful which is יש אחר ביאה אחר ביאה פסולה. yesh
achar biah achar biah pesula. Yes. A חליצה after a חליצה's already
been done really will have no effect. Right, won't פסול anybody? That's
true. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this, אמר רבא. amar
Rava. So that's just sort of explaining some of the foundations of
the משנה mishna without really getting into the details. Now we're going
to get into the debate of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and the
חכמים. Chachamim. אמר רבא. amar Rava. מאי טעמא דרבן גמליאל? mai ta'ama
deRabban Gamliel? What's the reason of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that says
יש מאמר אחר מאמר ויש גט אחר גט? yesh maamar achar maamar
veyesh get achar get? Right, even by מאמר maamar and גט רבנן,
he says that those things are, I'm sorry, אין מאמר אחר מאמר.
ein maamar achar maamar. I got confused. Whether that even the רבנן
מאמר maamar and גט do are basically complete, there's nothing that comes
afterwards. Okay, now you would say the simplest thing to say about
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is he just feels that these רבנן institutions,
מאמר maamar and גט, just do a hundred percent. So the same
way there's no קידושין after קידושין at a דאורייתא level, there's no
מאמר maamar after מאמר, maamar there's no גט after a גט when
גט is operating דאורייתא. There's no גט after גט when it's דרבנן.
derabanan However, the problem is is that תוספות, Tosafot, רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot both point out is that it sounds like in the
משנה that he only says אין מאמר אחר מאמר ואין גט אחר
גט. ein maamar achar maamar ve'ein get achar get. It sounds like
he would say though let's say מאמר maamar. after גט or גט
after מאמר maamar, would be meaningful. So if he really feels that
מאמר maamar does everything at least at a דרבנן derabanan level, then
if you did another דרבנן derabanan act, whether it was מאמר maamar
whether it was גט, it should be meaningless, right? You're basically דרבנן
derabbanan considered married to this woman. Who cares if you do now
another מאמר maamar, to the other woman or גט to the other
or whatever, meaning דאורייתא you should be done, I mean דרבנן playing
field you should be done. But he doesn't say that. He says
only a מאמר maamar following מאמר maamar, is nothing and a גט
following a גט is nothing. But it sounds like if you... And
match there is still something that can be done. So why is
that? So let's take a look. מאי טעמא דרבן גמליאל, Mai taama
deRabban Gamliel, what's the reasoning of רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel? דמספקא ליה
גט אי דחי אי לא דחי מאמר אי קני אי לא קני.
Demaspeka lei get ee dachi ee lo dachi maamar ee kani ee
lo kani. He doesn't know if גט is a hundred percent or
zero, or מאמר maamar is that a hundred percent קונה koneh or
zero.
So let's take a look. אי לא קני, Ee lo kani, גט
אי דחי אי לא דחי. get ee dachi ee lo dachi. So
גט he doesn't know if that completely
pushes off like all the wives at a דרבנן level we're talking
or not. אי קא מדחי, Ee ka madchi, so if it pushed
off wife number one, Sarah, when he gave a גט, so בתר
מאי קא עביד? basar mai ka avid? So the second גט to
Rivka is meaningless. He's already pushed off the wives, meaning it's not
limited to which wife, it just pushes off all the wives. So
he says a גט either pushes off all the wives or it
doesn't. If it pushes off all the wives, then the second גט
is meaningless. ואי קמא לא דחי, Ve-ee kama lo dachi, if it
didn't fully push off the wives, not all the wives and not
Sarah, didn't fully push her off. So ואי קמא לא דחי, ve-ee
kama lo dachi, so בתר נמי לא דחי. basar nami lo dachi.
So if it didn't do anything to Sarah, it didn't do anything
to Rivka. Okay, which is funny, it's like he's not accepting like
a middle state, like a quasi דוחה. docheh. That's exactly, it either
works or it doesn't work, because if it works it works for
all the wives, and if it doesn't work it doesn't work for
any. So the first wife, Sarah, obviously had some status, the גט
was given to her, but the second one, and maybe it was
effective, but the second one, if it was effective by Sarah then
there's nothing left to be done with the second גט because it's
effective for all the wives. And if it wasn't effective by Sarah,
all the more so it's not going to be effective for the
other wives. So the only person who could be effective is the
first wife. Okay. בתר נמי לא קא עביד. Basar nami lo kavid.
ואי קמא לא קני, Ve-ee kama lo kani, מאמר אי קני אי
לא קני, maamar ee kani ee lo kani, same by מאמר, maamar?
it either works fully or not at all. מאמר אי קני אי
לא קני. Maamar ee kani ee lo kani. ואי קמא קני, Ve-ee
kama kani, if it works for Sarah, so then he's married to
Sarah, so בתר מאי קא עביד? basar mai ka avid? So then
it's meaningless. Once there's a status of יבום with Sarah, anything done
with Rivka is meaningless. So Rivka's status doesn't change. ואי קמא לא
קני, Ve-ee kama lo kani, and if it wasn't considered meaningful for
Sarah, so בתר נמי לא קני, basar nami lo kani, then it's
zero, then it's meaningless for even the second one. Okay, so it's
either all or it's nothing. So therefore the first one is meaningful
because it might be all, but the second one is certainly not
meaningful. So איתיביה אביי, Eitiveih Abaye, Abaye asked this, ומודה רבן גמליאל,
u-modeh Rabban Gamliel, Rabban Gamliel does concede שיש גט אחר מאמר ומאמר
אחר גט. she-yesh get achar maamar u-maamar achar get. This is what
we were saying, that you can mix and match them. Now that's
not necessarily a problem. וגט אחר ביאה ומאמר, Ve-get achar biah u-maamar,
and a גט and a גט can come אחר ביאה ומאמר achar
biah u-maamar after a ביאה that followed a מאמר, maamar that was
ביאה פסולה, biah pesulah, right? You did מאמר maamar with one wife,
ביאה with the other, so that's again not a full ביאה because
it came after something. So therefore a גט afterwards is meaningful. ומאמר
אחר ביאה או גט, U-maamar achar biah o get, and similarly a
מאמר can come after a ביאה that followed a גט. Again that
would be a ביאה פסולה. biah pesulah. Okay, now what's his question?
ואי מספקא ליה לרבן גמליאל, Ve-ee misapka leih le-Rabban Gamliel, if Rabban
Gamliel has a doubt, תיהוי כביאה דלכתחילה דתקני. tehvei ke-biah de-lechatchila di-takni.
So he's not bothered with the idea of מאמר after a גט,
right? That idea of the mixing and the matching, that actually works,
right? Because why could a מאמר work after a גט? Because maybe
גט is zero. Right? He says he doesn't know it's a hundred
or zero. So you did גט with one woman and מאמר with
the other, so maybe גט was zero with the first woman and
מאמר with the second one was meaningful. So why מאמר works after
גט, that works within this model. Okay, is everybody with me? Right?
You know either מאמר is a hundred or zero, גט is a
hundred or zero, but they don't have to be the same. So
מאמר could work after גט or גט after מאמר because one could
be effective and the other not. Okay, but that's not his question.
His question is this case of ביאה פסולה. biah pesulah. Okay, the
case of ביאה פסולה biah pesulah is מאמר can come after what...
what's the case of ביאה פסולה? biah pesulah? גט אחר ביאה ומאמר.
Get achar biah u-maamar. So you have a case where he did
מאמר and then he did with woman number one, let's do it
over here, okay. So he went ahead and he did one, he
did מאמר with Sarah, okay, then he did ביאה with Rivka, which
makes it a ביאה פסולה biah pesulah because it came after מאמר
with Sarah. That's what we were talking about. And then he had
what did he have after that? Well no, but he also had
מאמר. Could also then he had a מאמר, okay, and then he
went ahead and he had a and he had a מאמר with
let's say wife number three, okay, Devorah, fine. Okay, now he says
like this, he says so why is this considered to be a
ביאה פסולה? biah pesulah? Remember, מאמר is either all or nothing according
to him, right? So if this was totally מאמר, right? If this
was totally good, right? So then this, so then this type of
ביאה sort of you know that gets ignored but this is like
מאמר after מאמר, right? Meaning why does this ביאה change this third
thing from being מאמר after מאמר? Okay, if it was nothing, so
then it's מאמר after ביאה, right? And that should be nothing, אין
אחר ביאה פסולה כלום. ein achar biah pesulah klum. If מאמר is
a hundred percent... then the, then the ביאה *biah* shouldn't be meaningful,
right? Because this was like a hundred percent. So then this ביאה
*biah*,
so then this ביאה *biah* shouldn't be meaningful, should be a מאמר
*maamar* after מאמר *maamar*. Why is it that how does a ביאה
פסולה *biah psula* get in there? Let's take a look at that
in the גמרא *Gemara*. Let's take a look. It says it says
אביי *Abaye* says like this, he says, and if you think like
רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*, ואי סלקא דעתך דרבן גמליאל הויא
כביאה דלכתחילה ותקני
*ve'i salka daitach derabban gamliel havyah keviah delechatchila vetikni*, so then why
isn't the ביאה *biah* just like a totally good ביאה *biah* meaning,
והא תנן הביאה בזמן שהיא בתחילה אין אחריה כלום *veha tenan habiah
bizman shehi vetchila ein achareha klum*. Let me just re-check רש"י *Rashi*
to make sure I've explained this as well as I can. Hold
on. Yeah, that's what רש"י *Rashi* says. He says if this is
a hundred or zero, so make up your mind. If this is
a hundred, then this is nothing and this is nothing. Okay, I
mean it's a little funny because even if it's a hundred, it's
only a hundred rabbinically, this is still a דאורייתא *d'oraissa* ביאה *biah*,
but okay. If it's a hundred percent, then this should be nothing
and then it should be מאמר אחר מאמר *maamar achar maamar*. If
it's zero percent, then therefore it shouldn't work. And therefore and therefore
this should not be problematic. Okay, because it's like מאמר *maamar* after
מאמר *maamar*, right?
מאמר אחר מאמר *maamar achar
maamar* doesn't work, doesn't do anything. Right, exactly. And if this is
and if this is and if this is a hundred percent, if
this is zero percent, then this should work. And then this should
not be do anything. So why is it if it's either zero
or a hundred, then this doesn't make any sense?
They're all so why so plural?
Yeah, they're all they're wives of ראובן *Reuven*. אלא אמר אביי *ella
amar Abaye*, so clearly it means what we're clearly seeing is that
this is not either zero or a hundred. This is something quasi.
Because it's quasi, then it makes the ביאה *biah* a problematic ביאה
*biah* and then makes this מאמר *maamar* after it a problematic מאמר
*maamar*, but so let's take a look at how אביי *Abaye* explains
it. אלא אמר אביי לא נצרכה אלא לרבן גמליאל בגט אחר מאמר
דקני *ella amar Abaye lo nitzrecha ela lerabban gamliel beget achar maamar
dekani*. No, no, no, no, he believes that these things actually do
it, maybe maybe in a quasi way, but it's not either zero
or a hundred. מי אי אמרו רבנן האי יבמה בחד צד מהני
בה גט ובחד צד מהני בה מאמר *mi i amru rabanan hai
yivama bechad tzad mehani bah get uvechad tzad mehani bah maamar*. So
he says, however it works like fifty percent, but on the same
fifty percent. I'll read and then explain. גט אחר גט לא דחי
דהא דחיה לה קמא *get achar get lo dachi deha dacha leh
kama*. A גט *get* after גט *get* doesn't do anything because the
first one was already דוחה *doche*. ומאמר קמא מאמר לא קני דהא
קניה לה קמא *umaamar kama maamar lo kani deha kanyeh leh kama*.
And a מאמר *maamar* after מאמר *maamar* doesn't because the first one
was already קונה *koneh*. Meaning, so basically he says that
the
idea is that you've got a what do you call it? If
you've got a here, here's this woman, שרה *Sarah*, okay. Now she's
got a it's like two halves, okay? It's like, you know, I
don't know, side A and side B, okay? This is the half
that you can do of the זיקה *zika* that you can I
don't know how else to explain this, this is the half of
the זיקה *zika* that you can like effect the קניין *kinyan* with.
So somebody goes ahead and does a מאמר *maamar*, he totally sort
of effects this part, it's not a hundred percent, it's not ביאה
*biah*, but he this half of the זיקה *zika*, right, if we
sort of say that this is like the זיקה *zika*, the זיקה
*zika*'s comprised of two parts. Okay, so he connects with her on
half of the זיקה *zika*, okay? But it does not completely solidify
the relationship, it's not ביאה *biah*. So there's another half that's left
over. That other half however can only be affected, right, by not
by another you know, by an act of by a גט *get*.
Like this is the half that the גט *get* works on, this
is the half the מאמר *maamar* works on, this is the half
the גט *get* works on. Okay, so if he does a מאמר
*maamar* to שרה *Sarah*, okay, he's like connected to her fifty percent
of the way in terms of the זיקה *zika*. Okay, another מאמר
*maamar* however does nothing, right? It just tries to fill up into
this column but it it doesn't that that half is already is
already is already claimed, okay? So a מאמר *maamar* after מאמר *maamar*
doesn't do anything. A גט *get* after מאמר *maamar* however does do
something because it only operated on fifty percent, and this גט *get*
however sort of you know, at least at a rabbinic level like
releases the other fifty percent of the זיקה *zika*. Okay, so a
גט *get* after a גט *get* doesn't do anything. I don't know,
this is the way he's explaining it. A גט *get* after גט
*get* doesn't do anything because that fifty percent she's already been she's
already been released from. But a גט *get* after but a מאמר
*maamar* after a גט *get* does something because the other fifty percent
hasn't been okay, so that's how he sort of sees it. Like
there's with every woman you can effect the זיקה *zika*, strengthen it
halfway with the מאמר *maamar*, and the other part of the זיקה
*zika* you can release with the גט *get*. But you can't have
two of the same, but you can switch. So because it works
halfway in the case of שרה *Sarah*, רבקה *Rivka*, and דבורה *Devorah*
here, right, so you did here a מאמר *maamar* halfway a מאמר
*maamar*, and then you had a ביאה *biah*, this was actually a
ביאה פסולה *biah psula*. It wasn't either all or nothing, because you
still had a quasi-זיקה *zika* to שרה *Sarah*. You had this part
of the זיקה *zika* hadn't been released. So this was doing a
ביאה *biah* with the second
wife but it's a, but it's not complete. So this ביאה *biah*,
if it were complete, then this ביאה *biah* would be meaningless. If
it were nothing, then this ביאה *biah* would be meaningful. If it's
halfway, then this ביאה *biah* is problematic because now you've forged a
relationship with רבקה *Rifkah*, and you still have a relationship with שרה
*Sarah*. And that makes it into a ביאה פסולה *biah pesulah*. And
because it becomes a ביאה פסולה *biah pesulah*, the מאמר *maamar* that
follows here is following a is following a ביאה פסולה *biah pesulah*.
It's not, right? The other way, this was all or nothing, you
either had no ביאה *biah* or you had no מאמר *maamar*. Here
you always had half of it, which makes the next one into
a ביאה פסולה *biah pesulah*. All right, clear clear enough? As clear
as we're going to get? Yeah.
But could you, could you show, could you just which words exactly
here fit this model like... Sure.
פיסל להו רבן גמליאל דדחיא במאמר דקני *Pisel lehu Rabban Gamliel de-dachya
b'maamar dekoni*. ומיחו *Umihu*, אמר רבנן *amar Rabbanan*, היי יבמה בחד צד
מהני בה גט *hai yevama be-chad tzad mehani bah get* on half
of her the גט *get* is effective, ובחד צד מהני בה מאמר
*u-ve-chad tzad mehani bah maamar*. גט אחר גט לא דחי דדחיה לקמא
*Get achar get lo dacha de-dachya lekama*. The first גט *get*, right,
was already pushed her away and the second one doesn't like affect,
it comes afterwards. ומאמר אחר מאמר לא קני דהקני לקמא *u-maamar achar
maamar lo kani de-hakni lekama*. גט אחר מאמר ומאמר אחר גט היי
מהני לסתור דחייה והיי מהני לסתור קנייה *Get achar maamar u-maamar achar
get hai mehani lister dahiya vehai mehani lister kniya*. Half of the
one of them is doing the דחיה *dahiya* and the other is
doing the קנייה *kniya*, so it's a quasi. Okay. ורבנן *Ve-Rabbanan*, and
that's why and that's why he says that either you can't have
two of the same, but you can have two of different, not
because of a ספק *safek* but because of halfway, but a specific
halfway, which also means that the ביאה *biah* that follows it is
a ביאה פסולה *biah pesulah*. It's not either a hundred percent ביאה
*biah* or a zero percent ביאה *biah*, it's a ביאה פסולה *biah
pesulah* because what happened before did happen, it just happened halfway. ורבנן
*Ve-Rabbanan*, and the rabbis will say, כל חד וחד תקינו ליה רבנן
גט ומאמר ביבמה *Kol chad ve-chad tikinu lei Rabbanan get u-maamar be-yevama*.
Every every brother-in-law, the rabbis established a גט *get* and a מאמר
*maamar* with his sister-in-law. והאי ביאה פסולה עדיפא *Ve-hai biah pesulah adifa*.
Okay, now, what does that mean? It means, one minute. So what
the
what the רבנן *Rabbanan* would say back is they would say that
okay here when brother-in-law one, שמעון *Shimon*, does this, he did this
מאמר *maamar* with her. Now, what what in order to explain רבן
גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*, right, אין מאמר אחר מאמר *ein maamar achar maamar*
means not only for שרה *Sarah* is a if he tried to
do another מאמר *maamar* for שרה *Sarah* anyway that'd be meaningless, he'd
already done a מאמר *maamar* with שרה *Sarah*. So by saying אין
מאמר אחר מאמר *ein maamar achar maamar* what you're actually saying is
that even if לוי *Levi* comes and tries to do another מאמר
*maamar* with שרה *Sarah*, no, that relationship has already been forged, right?
By the way, what you're also saying, just not to confuse you,
but okay, is if he now tried to do something with רבקה
*Rifkah*, a מאמר *maamar* would be meaningless. When he says that he's
done fifty percent, not only has he done fifty percent of forging
the relationship with שרה *Sarah*, but somehow of like the entire class
of sister-in-laws, that מאמר *maamar* slot has been filled. So comes along
the רבנן *Rabbanan* and they say, we don't disagree like with this
type of way of looking at it, but what we do say
is, first of all, every sister-in-law you can also forge the relationship
to, so every sister-in-law you have a מאמר *maamar* and a גט
*get* slot, so even though he's connected here, there's nothing to prevent
him from doing a similar type of relationship there, that makes sense.
And they say every brother-in-law also has their own, as it were,
slot. So therefore שמעון *Shimon* maybe filled up his מאמר *maamar* slot
there with שרה *Sarah*, but לוי *Levi* can come and now also
do an act of מאמר *maamar* with שרה *Sarah*, right, that also
would somehow be meaningful. Okay, I don't know what to say. So
please, let's worry about the what, the why is like, the what
is hard enough. Okay, so he says the rabbis disagree and they
say, yes, except that every single brother-in-law and for every sister-in-law one
might add, also has the ability to do this. It's not you
don't look at them as a class. Okay, so it says like
this, ורבנן
*ve-Rabbanan*, and the rabbis would say back, כל חד וחד תקינו ליה
רבנן גט ומאמר ביבמה *kol chad ve-chad tikinu lei Rabbanan get u-maamar
be-yevama*. Every brother-in-law the rabbis established גט *get* or מאמר *maamar* with
each sister-in-law. Okay, so and therefore and therefore
that's the nature of the מחלוקת *machlokes*. Okay, everybody agrees that there's
half for יבום *yibbum* and half for half for מאמר *maamar* and
half for גט *get*, but the question is is it for all
the class of brother-in-laws or sister-in-laws or does each one have a
separate one? Okay, yes. Now, doesn't מאמר *maamar* reserve somebody for the...
yeah,
it makes her invalid to do it with any of the other
brother-in-laws.
How can there be another מאמר *maamar* of another brother in the
brother, if she's reserved? Yeah.
Like also her half is filled up with
שמעון *Shimon*.
Well, again, remember, any any type of a case of מאמר אחר
מאמר *maamar achar maamar*, גט אחר מאמר *get achar maamar*, once you've
done the first one, everything else is only going to make problems.
It's not going to give you any it's not going to give
you any of the rights. So when we say there's a
מאמר *maamar*... It's not effective, it's only effective to create problems. Okay.
So you're right, at this stage, once the first guy got in,
now you're right, it makes more sense to say that there's a
מאמר *ma'amar* after מאמר *ma'amar* for a different woman than that's for
a different brother for the same woman. That I agree. But what
the ספרי *Sifrei* is saying is once they sort of gave any
brother the right to do מאמר *ma'amar* and any brother the right
to do גט *get*, so then somehow conceptually the second one still
is meaningful enough to create problems, not to give him any of
those privileges or rights or whatever, but enough to create problems. This
is all דרבנן *d'rabbanan*, right,
so it's like brother one can say 'I'll marry you' and brother
two can say 'no, I'll marry you'.
Right, but brother, they both can't. All right, we're moving on.
What does it do to the first brother's מאמר *ma'amar* though?
No, that's why, yeah, once these types of things start happening, then
you have to just give a lot of גטין *getin* and חליצות
*chalitzos* and גטין *getin*, right. Like I think that's the basic rule,
once these problems start happening, you just have to like clean it
up.
The משנה *Mishnah* in the מסכת *Masechet* was written by Sophie, you
understand.
All right, so now it goes like this. It says...
Okay, it says like this: והשתא *v'hashtah*, and now we're going back
to understanding why according to רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*, the case about,
about, about the case of
Sarah,
Rivka, I don't know, Rachel, Leah, why the case here about that
he first he did מאמר *ma'amar*, ביאה
*bi'ah*, and then מאמר *ma'amar*, right? And we said that because this
is basically 50%, this becomes ביאה פסולה *bi'ah psulah*, and then this
becomes מאמר *ma'amar* after ביאה פסולה *bi'ah psulah*, and that becomes not
just מאמר *ma'amar* after מאמר *ma'amar*, and that becomes problematic. So let's
take a look at how the גמרא *Gemara* explains that.
Okay... Okay, והאי ביאה
פסולה עדיפה ממאמר *v'hai bi'ah psulah adifa mi'ma'amar* is better than the
first מאמר *ma'amar*, which basically means is better in the sense that
it creates an overlay of the first מאמר *ma'amar*, וגריעה ממאמר *v'gri'ah
mi'ma'amar*, and in a way it's worse than מאמר *ma'amar*. עדיפה ממאמר
*adifa mi'ma'amar*, it's better than the first מאמר *ma'amar*, דאילו מאמר אחר
מאמר לא מהני *d'ilu ma'amar achar ma'amar lo mahani*, because if it
had just been מאמר *ma'amar* אחר *achar* מאמר *ma'amar*, it would be
nothing; they'd be trying to sort of overlap the same slot and
it wouldn't do anything. לא מהני *lo mahani*. ואילו ביאה אחר מאמר
מהני *v'ilu bi'ah achar ma'amar mahani*, but because the ביאה *bi'ah* came
in, that sort of now dominated. And we sort of ignore the
fact that a מאמר *ma'amar* preceded it, and we look at it
as that there's ביאה *bi'ah*, and then מאמר *ma'amar* after ביאה *bi'ah*.
Well, that's a different type of a relationship, and therefore the second
מאמר *ma'amar* can be meaningful. Okay? So it took over the presence
of the first מאמר *ma'amar*. מהני
*mahani*. Where were we? וגריעה ממאמר *v'gri'ah mi'ma'amar*, but it's weaker, דאילו
מאמר אחר גט קני לכולה שיורה דגט *d'ilu ma'amar achar get kani
l'kula shi'ura d'get*, because if a מאמר *ma'amar* came after a גט
*get*, then it would sort of fill up the other half, as
it were. ואילו ביאה אחר גט לא קני לכולה שיורה דגט *v'ilu
bi'ah achar get lo kani l'kulo shi'ura d'get*. Let's say this wasn't
a מאמר *ma'amar*, let's say this was a גט *get*. Okay? Right?
So if that were a גט *get*. So if this were a
מאמר *ma'amar* after a גט *get*, the מאמר *ma'amar* would fill slot
number two, as it were, and מאמר *ma'amar* after מאמר *ma'amar* would
similarly not do anything, right? But because it's a ביאה *bi'ah* after
a גט *get*, okay, it is weaker and it doesn't somehow totally,
you know, fill slot number two and allows the מאמר *ma'amar* afterwards
to still, you know, still come out and be binding. Meaning the
point is is that, look, it is... whatever. If you have this
case, it's a little bit funny, right? Because this is מאמר *ma'amar*
after מאמר *ma'amar* and a ביאה *bi'ah* in the middle should, if
anything, not make it worse, it's just another way of once again
saying like the relationship has already been forged ahead of time in
a sense. And if a מאמר *ma'amar*... if the relationship was forged
once and another מאמר *ma'amar* doesn't do anything, so if another relationship
has been forged, it should even more make the מאמר *ma'amar*, like
you know, the third מאמר *ma'amar* irrelevant. No, no, this is רבן
גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*. Okay. But but nevertheless, because the ביאה *bi'ah* comes
after, the ביאה *bi'ah* since it's anyway דאורייתא *d'oraisa* sort of dominates,
allows us to ignore the מאמר *ma'amar* and to say now we're
going to look at ביאה *bi'ah* מאמר *ma'amar*, now they're somehow different,
so the second
מאמר *ma'amar* is doing something because
it's relative to the ביאה *bi'ah*. That's the way we say the
ביאה *bi'ah* is stronger. But we say the ביאה *bi'ah* is weaker
because if the case because if it really were, you know, I
mean again it's funny why I had to shift to גט *get*,
you could have said because if it really were just about the
ביאה *bi'ah*, if the ביאה *bi'ah* itself had a stronger presence than
a מאמר *ma'amar*, then a מאמר *ma'amar* after ביאה *bi'ah* should be
just as meaningless as a מאמר *ma'amar* after a מאמר *ma'amar*. Okay.
So the way the גמרא *Gemara* also says it is as if
that's a ביאה *bi'ah* is after a גט *get*, right, why is
this מאמר *ma'amar* meaningful? Why don't we say... Why don't we say
this מאמר *ma'amar* is trying to fill the slot as it were
that's already been filled by the ביאה *biah* and it if it
can't and it can't do it? So you know if this slot
were filled by מאמר *ma'amar* right the second מאמר *ma'amar* would be
meaningless but somehow because it's filled by ביאה *biah* the second מאמר
*ma'amar* is meaningful. So in a way the ביאה *biah* takes over
the like if a מאמר *ma'amar* preceded it basically you know is
strong enough to make us ignore what preceded yes because right because
otherwise we would just call it מאמר *ma'amar* after מאמר *ma'amar* and
at the same time it's weaker than a מאמר *ma'amar* because if
this was מאמר *ma'amar* מאמר *ma'amar* you'd also be okay but because
we
view this
as somewhat weaker than מאמר *ma'amar* in a
certain way so the second מאמר *ma'amar* remains meaningful. Okay stronger than
מאמר *ma'amar* to allow
us to ignore
it
and it's weaker than
מאמר *ma'amar* to allow the second מאמר *ma'amar* I have no idea.
All right moving on. All right okay so
this means אדיף ממאמר וגריע ממאמר *adif m'ma'amar v'garei m'ma'amar*. אדיף ממאמר
דאי מאמר אחר מאמר לא מהני ואילו ביאה אחר מאמר מהני *adif
m'ma'amar d'ee ma'amar achar
ma'amar lo mahani v'ilu biah achar ma'amar mahani*. וגריע ממאמר דאילו מאמר
אחר גט קני לכולה שיור דגט *v'garei m'ma'amar d'ilu ma'amar achar get
kani l'kula shiyur d'get* that if a מאמר *ma'amar* came after a
גט *get* you'd be done and then the next מאמר *ma'amar* would
be meaningless. ואילו ביאה אחר גט לא קני לכולה שיור דגט *v'ilu
biah achar get lo kani l'kula shiyur d'get* and the ביאה *biah*
afterwards does not end and the מאמר *ma'amar* that follows that is
still going to be problematic.
Okay fine. What the גט *get* remained left over left over. Okay
fine. Now you go on right. Okay תנו רבנן כיצד רבן גמליאל
אומר אין גט אחר גט *tanu rabanan keitzad Rabban Gamliel omer ein
get achar get*? What's the case of אין גט אחר גט *ein
get achar get*? שתי יבמות שנפלו לפני יבם אחד *shtei yevamot shenaplu
lifnei yavam echad* two sisters-in-law. ונתן גט לזו וגט לזו *v'natan get
l'zo v'get l'zo*. רבן גמליאל אומר חולץ לראשונה ואסור בקרובותיה *Rabban Gamliel
omer choletz l'rishona v'asur b'krovoteha*.
So the first one he does the חליצה *chalitzah* why don't he
do the חליצה *chalitzah* the second one I mean in theory you
could but don't because the second one is why hurt her status
to a כהן *Kohen*? You've given the גט *get* to the first
one what you did to the second is meaningless do חליצה *chalitzah*
to the first and you're אסור *asur* in her קרובות *krovot* ומותר
בקרובות שנייה *u'mutar b'krovot shniya* and like the גט *get* given to
the second one is completely meaningless and מותר *mutar* in the קרובות
*krovot*. וחכמים אומרים נתן גט לזו וגט לזו אסור בקרובות שתיהן *v'Chachamim
omrim natan get l'zo v'get l'zo asur b'krovot shteihen*. No the second
גט *get* is meaningful even with the second sister-in-law and it's like
she's your divorced wife and therefore you're אסור *asur* in the קרובות
*krovot*. And once it's meaningful once both of them are considered to
be מגורשת *megureshet* at least דרבנן *d'rabanan* וחליצה לאחת מהן *v'chalitzah l'achat
mehen* you can do חליצה *chalitzah* to either one because their status
has already been affected for a כהן *Kohen*. וכן אתה אומר בשני
יבמים ויבמה אחת *v'chen ata omer b'shnei yevamim v'yevama achat* the same
with two brothers-in-law and one sister-in-law. כיצד רבן גמליאל אומר *keitzad Rabban
Gamliel omer* so you could we won't play it up but you
can figure it out it's ראובן *Reuven* and שמעון *Shimon* if שמעון
*Shimon* gave the if ראובן *Reuven* gave a גט *get* to שרה
*Sarah* and then שמעון *Shimon* gave a גט *get* to שרה *Sarah*
according to רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* שמעון *Shimon*'s status has no is
meaningless to שרה *Sarah* and he's מותר *mutar* in her relative and
according to the חכמים *Chachamim* no שמעון *Shimon* also becomes like שרה
*Sarah*'s ex-husband and is אסור *asur* in her relatives. כיצד רבן גמליאל
אומר אין מאמר אחר מאמר *keitzad Rabban Gamliel omer ein ma'amar achar
ma'amar*? What's the case of אין מאמר אחר מאמר *ein ma'amar achar
ma'amar*? שתי יבמות שנפלו לפני יבם אחד *shtei yevamot shenaplu lifnei yavam
echad*. So now we're going to start with the two sister-in-law cases.
ועשה מאמר בזו ומאמר בזו *v'asa ma'amar b'zo u'ma'amar b'zo*. He did
a מאמר *ma'amar* with both. רבן גמליאל אומר *Rabban Gamliel omer* so
the רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says only the one that was done
with שרה *Sarah*'s meaningful. נותן גט לראשונה וחולץ לה ואסור בקרובותיה *noten
get l'rishona v'choletz lah v'asur b'krovoteha*. So now if שרה *Sarah*'s the
one that he has done the מאמר *ma'amar* he has to give
her a גט *get* for his מאמר *ma'amar* and he has to
do חליצה *chalitzah*. Again don't do חליצה *chalitzah* with רחל *Rachel* because
why hurt her status? שרה *Sarah*'s status is already the one that
is going to be the מגורשת *megureshet* and the חלוצה *chalutza* ואסור
בקרובותיה ומותר בקרובות שנייה *v'asur b'krovoteha u'mutar b'krovot shniya* and with רחל
*Rachel* he's totally fine. וחכמים אומרים נותן גט לשתיהן *v'Chachamim omrim noten
get l'shteihen*. No the מאמר *ma'amar* with the second one also is
meaningful so they both need a גט *get*. Once they both need
a גט *get* ואסור בקרובות שתיהן *v'asur b'krovot shteihen* they're both considered
ex-wives he's אסור *asur* with both their relatives וחליצה לאחת מהן *v'chalitzah
l'achat mehen* and a חליצה *chalitzah* to either one. Again they're both
considered גרושה *grusha* so it doesn't matter who you're going to do
חליצה *chalitzah* with. וכן אתה אומר בשני יבמים ויבמה אחת *v'chen ata
omer b'shnei yevamim v'yevama achat* the same would be true if it
were two brothers-in-law and one sister-in-law and both of them did מאמר
*ma'amar* with the same woman according to רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* the
second brother-in-law would... be meaningless and according to the חכמים *Chachamim*, no,
even he would have to give a גט *get* and be אסור
*osser* in the relatives. אמר מר *amar mar*: נותן גט לזו וגט
לזו *nosein get l'zu v'get l'zu*, the, my god, the Tannaitic material
is so much easier than this and the Amoraic one. אמר מר
*amar mar*: נותן גט לזו וגט לזו *nosein get l'zu v'get l'zu*,
רבן גמליאל אומר *Rabban Gamliel omeir*, חולץ לראשונה *choletz l'rishonah* ואסור בקרובותיה
*v'assur bikrovoseha* ומותר בקרובות שנייה
*u'mutar bikrovos shniyah*. Okay, so רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says no, you
in that case where you did two gets, just focus on the
first one and do a חליצה *chalitzah*.
Okay, okay. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this, לימא תהוי תיובתא
דשמואל *leima tehvei tiyuvta d'Shmuel*. This will be a contradiction to שמואל
*Shmuel*. דאמר שמואל *d'amar Shmuel*, שמואל *Shmuel* says, חלץ לבעלת הגט לא
נפטרה צרה *chalatz l'ba'alas haget lo nifterah tzarah*. 'Cause שמואל *Shmuel* you
might remember said a long time ago that if a person did
a חליצה *chalitzah* in a case where, now this was a גט
*get* about, again, two sister-in-laws and he gave a גט *get* to
one of them and then he did חליצה *chalitzah*. So שמואל *Shmuel*
says since he gave a גט *get* to שרה *Sarah*, the relationship
to שרה *Sarah* has already been weakened by the גט *get*. So
the חליצה *chalitzah* he's now going to do to שרה *Sarah* is
similar to this idea of ביאה פסולה *biah psulah*, it's like a
חליצה פסולה *chalitzah psulah*, it's like a weaker חליצה *chalitzah*. And since
it's a weaker חליצה *chalitzah* because it followed a גט *get*, it
doesn't exempt the other co-wives and he has to do a חליצה
*chalitzah* with all of the co-wives. So we're not saying that here.
Here רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* is saying you gave a גט *get*
to both, just do a חליצה *chalitzah* with the first wife and
be done with it. But what about שמואל *Shmuel*'s idea? It's a
weaker חליצה *chalitzah*, he's got to do חליצה *chalitzah* with everyone. So
it says דאמר שמואל חלץ לבעלת הגט לא נפטרה צרה *d'amar Shmuel
chalatz l'ba'alas haget lo nifterah tzarah*. אמר לך שמואל *amar lach Shmuel*,
כי אמינא אנא *ki amina ana*, when did I say that you
have to do a חליצה *chalitzah* with all the co-wives if a
חליצה *chalitzah* followed a גט *get*? אליבא דמאן דאמר יש זיקה *aliba
d'man d'amar yeish zikah*. If there is a זיקה *zikah* and then
the גט *get* weakened the זיקה *zikah*, the relationship, so the חליצה
*chalitzah* is seen as a weaker חליצה *chalitzah*. רבן גמליאל סבר אין
זיקה *Rabban Gamliel savar ein zikah*. But רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* holds
there is no זיקה *zikah*. There's a מצוה *mitzvah* of חליצה *chalitzah*
but there's no זיקה *zikah*. So a חליצה *chalitzah* that follows a
גט *get*, the reason we call it a weaker חליצה *chalitzah* is
we say the גט *get* weakened the relationship. But if I don't
start with a concept of זיקה *zikah*, I don't start with a
concept of a relationship, then the גט *get* didn't weaken it and
therefore the חליצה *chalitzah* is just as strong as any other חליצה
*chalitzah*. So you're right, שמואל *Shmuel* says I say a חליצה *chalitzah*
following a גט *get* is a weaker חליצה *chalitzah* and you have
to do it with all the co-wives, but רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*
says it's a normal חליצה *chalitzah* and you don't have to do
it with all the co-wives. Let's just read, I know we're about
a minute over, but let's just read a few more lines. ורבן
גמליאל סבר אין זיקה *v'Rabban Gamliel savar ein zikah*. Now the גמרא
*Gemara* thinks one minute, if that's what's going on here, that רבן
גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* is saying that there's no זיקה *zikah* and therefore
one חליצה *chalitzah* is enough, maybe, רש״י *Rashi* says this is not
based on any logic, just maybe we'll assume that the rabbis argue
on this point as well with רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*. מאי רבנן
סברי יש זיקה *mai rabanan savri yeish zikah*, that there is a
זיקה *zikah*. So let's take a look. This doesn't work. וקתני סיפא
וכן אתה אומר בשני יבמים ויבמה אחת *u'kasni seifa v'chein atah omeir
b'shnei yevamim v'yevamah achas*. Two brother-in-laws and one sister-in-law, ראובן *Reuven* and
שמעון *Shimon* with שרה *Sarah*. לימא תהוי תיובתא דרבה בר *leima tehvei
tiyuvta d'Rabba bar*. You know what? I think we have to end
here. We're going to pick up with this tomorrow. Okay, it's going
to be too much to...